<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The captive (that hath long been in captivity) visited with the day-spring from on high. Or the prisoner (that hath fitten in the prison-house of woful darkness) freed into the everlasting light and covenant of God, in which perfect peace and satisfaction is Written by way of conference, and sent out into the world for the sake of those who have long groped upon the tops of the dark mountains, where the barrennesse and emptinesse is, without the knowledge of the true light to be their guide, that they (as in a glass) may see themselves, and read what hath been the cause why they have so long sought, and not found that they have sought for. Given forth especially for the sake of the scattered people in America, by one who labors for and waits to see the elect gathered from the four quarters of the earth, known by the name of Richard Pinder.</title>
            <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2094:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The captive (that hath long been in captivity) visited with the day-spring from on high. Or the prisoner (that hath fitten in the prison-house of woful darkness) freed into the everlasting light and covenant of God, in which perfect peace and satisfaction is Written by way of conference, and sent out into the world for the sake of those who have long groped upon the tops of the dark mountains, where the barrennesse and emptinesse is, without the knowledge of the true light to be their guide, that they (as in a glass) may see themselves, and read what hath been the cause why they have so long sought, and not found that they have sought for. Given forth especially for the sake of the scattered people in America, by one who labors for and waits to see the elect gathered from the four quarters of the earth, known by the name of Richard Pinder.</title>
                  <author>Pinder, Richard, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-39, [1], 40-45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons at the sign of the Bull and Mouth near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page is on A2; preliminary leaf lacking?.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 7  reads: The captive visited: &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>"Postscript" begins on p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenant theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35378:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35378:1"/>
            <p>The Captive (that hath long been in Captivity) VISITED with the Day-ſpring from on high.</p>
            <p>Or the Priſoner (that hath ſitten in the Priſon-houſe of woful darkneſs) freed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the everlaſting light and Covenant of God, in which perfect peace and ſatisfaction is.</p>
            <p>Written by way of Conference, and ſent out into the World for the ſake of thoſe who have long groped upon the tops of the dark mountains, where the barrenneſſe and emptineſſe is, without the knowledge of the true light to be their guide, that they (as in a glaſs) may ſee themſelves, and read what hath been the cauſe why they have ſo long ſought, and not found that they have ſought for.</p>
            <p>Given forth eſpecially for the ſake of the ſcattered peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>America,</hi> by one who labors for and waits to ſee the Elect gathered from the four Quarters of the earth, known by the name of <hi>Richard Pinder.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſay 9.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The people that walked in darkneſs have ſeen a great light, they that dwell in the Land of the ſhadow of Death, upon them hath the Light ſhined.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35378:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35378:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHat here is written is for the ſake of thoſe that long hath been deceived and kept in Captivity, by expecting to receive Light and power in thoſe things which are weak and beggarly, and ſo have been toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too and fro, in the night of wofull darkneſs, where the Captivity and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage is, out of which none but the Lord alone can deliver. Therefore this is written, that ſuch as hath long layne in it, (expecting freedom through thoſe things which they have been drawn to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve by the cunning devices and ſlights of men) that they may turn their minds, and expectations from Gadding abroad, to feel and know the appearance of the true Light in themſelves which Chriſt hath enlightened them withall, and that by it they may ſearch themſelves, and ſee what hath kept them in Captivity, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35378:3"/>with the Light they may be led from it; for to that end doth the true light appear, as thou that reads and underſtands this following diſcourſe, will plainly ſee; and that there is no other way whereby thou or any can come out of Captivity, but through believing in the Light, which ſhews unto you your ſin and darkneſs, Which light is the free gift of God, and comes not through any outward means, but is freely placed in all to ſhew them ſin and tranſgreſſion which they are fallen into, and to lead out of it all them who believes in it, and follows it; but is the Condemnation of all who hates it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in the</hi> Iſland Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muda <date>the 9th day of the 3d. Mouth, <hi>1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35378:3"/>
            <head>THE CAPTIVE VISITED: &amp;c.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Captive.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>That have long ſitten in darkneſs, and under the ſhaddow of death, have heard a great Rumor of a</hi> light, <hi>that is broken forth; of which I would gladly be informed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Informer.</speaker>
               <p>Unto thee that hath long ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in darkneſs, and under the ſhaddow of death, is <hi>Light</hi> now ſprung forth, and the day from on high, viſiting of thee, to give thee the knowledge of ſalvation, by the remitting of thy ſins, under which thou long haſt been oppreſſed, and groaned to be delivered from; and the <hi>light</hi> (of which thou haſt heard ſuch a Rumor) is the way, which thy God hath prepared for thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſeeing I am yet in darkneſs, and that death doth yet over-ſhaddow me; where
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35378:4"/>muſt I come to the knowledge of this</hi> Light, <hi>of which I have heard ſuch a Rumor, &amp; which thou ſaith my God hath prepared for my deliverance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Inform.</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>Seeing thou ſeemeſt to make ſuch diligent enquiry concerning the <hi>Light,</hi> a Rumor of which thou ſaieſt thou haſt heard, and which I told thee, thy God hath prepared for thy deliverance; it therefore appeareth plainly unto me thou haſt ſome deſires to come out of the darkneſs, in which thou long haſt ſitten, and been over-ſhaddowed by. Therefore hearken and give ear, for the words of my mouth ſhall be words of truth, and eaſie to be underſtood as thou enclines unto the fear of the Lord. The <hi>Light</hi> which thou enquires after, and of which thou haſt heard a Rumor, and which I told thee thy God had prepared for thy deliverance, to give thee the knowledge of ſalvation through the remiting of thy ſins, under which thou haſt long been oppreſſed, (that is it which ſhines into thy own Conſcience, and lets thee ſee how darkneſs hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over thee, and how thou by it haſt been ſubjected unto vanity, and how ſin by the Power of it hath been brought forth, which hath brought forth death, which doth yet over-ſhaddow thee, that if ever thou can come to the knowledge of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35378:4"/>
                  <hi>Light,</hi> ſo as to lead thee out of darkneſs, which hath been the cauſe of all thy miſery, thou muſt own it, in its appearance, which is in giving thee to ſee ſin, and in reproving thee for it; to the end that thy heart might be broken off from it, and by the <hi>Light</hi> joyned unto God, who hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortallity, and dwelleth in the <hi>Light,</hi> with whom thy Souls peace is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Captive. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what nearer am</hi> I <hi>for this ſeeing that I am in darkneſs, and that death ſtill over-ſhaddoweth me, and that my ſins ſtill prevaile over me, though indeed as thou ſaiſt I find ſome ſmall deſires to be freed from this my darkneſs, but that which ſhould enable me, and give me Power over it, that I find not. And alſo thou ſaieſt that that is the</hi> Light <hi>which ſhines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my own Conſcience, (which ſhews me my own ſin and darkneſs) which the Lord hath prepared for my deliverance, which thing as yet I am not fully ſatisfied in; for the Light which ſhewed me my own ſin and reproved me for it, that I have neglected and not regarded, becauſe thoſe whom I follow for teaching, told me that it was but the Light of nature, or a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Light, or natural conſcience, and told me it was not ſufficient to lead out of ſin, and to give Power over it; but told me of a greater Light and power that ſhould come by hearing them preach, and uſing them things which they call Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35378:5"/>and that that light and power which ſhould come that way, ſhould free me from the condemning power of ſin, though not from that power by which it is brought forth. That as for this Light in my own Conſcience which thou tells me of, I have not at all regarded, but have altogether rejected it, and diſ-eſteemed of it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe whom I looked upon to be Chriſts Miniſters, told me that is was but natural, and not ſufficient to guid me unto God; neither with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all could I comprehend it my ſelf with all my wiſdom; that I have looked upon it to be no more then the Light of nature, though indeed I found it preſent at all times, (namely the light in my own Conſcience) checking, and reproving me for many ſins that were commited in ſecret, which no mortal eye ſaw me commit; that if thou or any who have believed in it and obeyed it, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto me in truth what the operation of it hath been, and what it hath wrought for ye, and what it hath led you into, and what it hath led ye from, I ſhould lend a diligent eare; for indeed I have vſed all the waies and means which the aforeſaid Teachers (whom I looked upon to be Chriſts Miniſters) told me was the worſhip of God and his Ordinances, which they told me I muſt wait for the appearance of the King of Peace in, whoſe Salvation my Soul hath longed after; but toſſed from Mountain to Hill I have been, and muſt needs confeſs by wofull
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35378:5"/>experience, that as yet the reſting place I have not found, neither am I any more ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my ſelf, which is the way to it then I was at firſt; I did adhere to thoſe Teachers that told me the way to it was by hearing them give their meanings upon the Scriptures, which they told me was preaching of the word, and that by hearing them faith ſhould be wrought, which thing I have been very diligent in; but alas no victory over my ſin I find; that gladly would I be further informed concerning this Light within, of which I have heard ſuch a Rumor, and which by ſo many both Teachers and people is ſpoken againſt as a thing not ſufficient to Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Inform.</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>Well, thy querie or rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is ſomething long; but perceiving thou haſt made it from the honeſty of thy heart, and from a true ſence of thy preſent ſtate, and condition, and doth in plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſire to be informed; therefore the Lord hath the more opened my heart to declare unto thee thoſe things which hath been hidden from thine eyes; that I ſhall endeavour, by the aſſiſtance of the light which comprehends all darkneſs, to inform thee therein. I perceive this is thy mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the beginning of thy laſt querie, that thou art no nearer for ſeeing thy ſin and darkneſs, ſeeing that ſtill thou art over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by it, and that it prevails againſt thee.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35378:6"/>
               <p>Its true, ſo long as thou doth not believe in the light (marke that) which ſhews thee thy ſin, and darkneſs, but hates it, ſo long thou art made no nearer to God by it, for it remains in thee, judging, reproving, and condemning thee, in whatſoever thou takes in hand, in that the curſed nature is head in thee, in which is an unreconcible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt God, who hath enlightned thee with his holy gift that through it thou mighteſt be redeemed out of the enmity, and made alive unto him who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned thee and for this end the Lord by his light which; he hath placed in thee, ſhews thee the darkneſs &amp; the enmity which is in thy own mind, by which thou haſt been led aſide and captivated, willing thee to turn from it, by reproving thee for every work, word, and thought that is brought forth by the power of it, which is the power of darkneſs; that ſo long as thou takes not heed unto that which ſhews thee darkneſs, thou takes part and yields thy ſtrength to the man of ſin, who by his power doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs thoſe ſmal deſires which thou ſaith thou ſometimes hath to be freed from the darkneſs; and ſo that which ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thee and give thee power to the bringing forth thoſe deſires, hath been trampled upon (namely the light which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35378:6"/>reproved thee for thy ſin) and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded according to thy own confeſſion; that thou was not like to receive power to over-come thy ſin, for it was they that received Chriſt (the true light) that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power to become the Sons of God, even thoſe that did believe in his Name; ſo in that thou haſt not believed in his light which he hath enlightened thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, thy ſin hath remained, and hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt thee, which hath brought forth death, under the ſhaddow of which thou yet ſitteth as thou confeſſeth; and thou ſaith thou art not as yet ſatisfied, that that is the light which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thy deliverance, which ſhines in thy own conſcience, and ſheweth thee thy ſin, and darkneſs. O yes, thats the true and eternal light which ſhines in thy own conſcience, and comes from Chriſt who is the Way, and the Truth and the Life; and thou having ſtumbled at this light which hath ſhewed thee thy ſin, and reproved thee for it, thou haſt ſtumbled at the way, the truth, and the life, and ſo hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the broad way in error and death; that ſatisfaction thou waſt not like to receive, being in the darkneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, where thou haſt called good evil, and evil good, and haſt put light for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35378:7"/>darkneſs, and darkneſs for light, and hath hearkened to ſuch Teachers as thou ſpeaks of, that told thee, the light that convinced thee of ſin was naturall, and Created, and thou having lent thy ear unto ſuch, thou haſt been deceived and led aſide from the path of life, and haſt ſpent thy money for that which is not bread, and thy labour for that which hath not ſatisfied, but haſt fed upon the husk and ſought the living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the dead; that thy Soul hath not delighted it ſelf in fatneſs, but thou haſt thought to have life in thoſe things which are empty, and unfruitfull, and hath followed the lying vanities of ſuch as hath told thee the light which ſhewed thee thy ſin, and darkneſs is natural; and the more thou liſtened unto ſuch, the further into darkneſs thou waſt led, and thou being in darkneſs was not like to comprehend the light by all thy wiſdom, for thy wiſdom is reprobated from God, and in that it ſtands, in that nature that is contrary to the light which is incomprehensible, though it ſhine in darkneſs, yet the darkneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend it, which maketh all them in whom the power of darkneſs beareth rule, ſo reproch it, and oppoſe it, withal their might and ſtrength; for by the light the bounds of it is ſet that it cannot paſs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35378:7"/>but it is ſeen and comprehended. So the light is that which is given to thee and all to lead out of darkneſs; therefore let thy eare be open to Inſtruction, and according to thy promiſe liſten with diligence, and apply thy heart to know that wiſdome which the fear of the Lord is the beginning of; for I ſhall open my mouth, and my tongue ſhal utter things wch hath been hid from the wiſe &amp; prudent, which God is now revealing unto Babes that are begotten by him, and born of the word of life, by which he hath opened my heart to declare unto thee, and to all that are weary of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented waies which man hath ſought out in the time of darkneſs, which thou ſaith thou haſt a deſire to come out of, and to be freed into the light of life; but thou haſt not known him that hath prevailed to open the Seale wherewith the Fountain of light, life, power, and glory is Sealed, and hath not been known open in this night of thick darkneſs, which thou ſaith in thy firſt querie unto me, thou haſt long ſitten in; ſo encline and bow thine eare, for the word of the Lord is towards thee, that out of this night of wofull darkneſs thou might be brought, in which thou haſt long travelled and groped without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true and everlaſting light, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35378:8"/>be thy guide; of which now I ſhall open my mouth to declare of its appearance and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration which hath been effectuall in me and many others, who through it hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy of the Lord, and am count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthy to bear teſtimony of the ſame among the Nations, which hath been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Clouds of darkneſs; and the Lords witneſſes we are that he is now riſen undoubtedly to deſtroy the covering of darkneſs, which hath been caſt over the face of all Nations; and this is the meſſage that we have received of him, and which we are ſent to declare, that he is light, and that in him is no darkneſs at all; and this Teſtimony we give of him unto all people, to the end they may be brought unto his light which he hath enlightened them withall, that in his Name they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and receive life everlaſting, that their ſins may be remitted and blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Captive. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But before thou begin to open thy mouth to declare of the appearance, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this light, I would gladly know if thou mean the light which is ſo much ſpoken of, that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the World that I may know whether I have a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it, or no.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35378:8"/>
                  <hi>Inform,</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>The light of the appearance and operation of which I am ready to open my mouth, is the light which Chriſt, (who is the Covenant given of the Father) hath enlightened every one withal, the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of which in every one is pure, living, and eternal, and is a ſwift witneſs in all, againſt all unrighteouſneſs of what kind or ſort ſoever; and the leaſt meaſure of it, is purity it ſelf, life it ſelf, righteouſneſs it ſelf; for it comes from him who is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all good, who was before all things, and is eternal, everlaſting, and endures for ever, who is the beginning and the end of all things, yet not known by any, but as they through his light which he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened them withal, comes to have their hearts and mindes redeemed out of all fading and periſhing things, which the hearts and minds of the Children of men are enclined unto in the fall, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in which the Lord of life and glory is not known; but he obeyed and ſits as Lord and King that hath ſubverted the hearts of all man-kind from their Maker, and keeps them in ſubjection unto himſelf, bringing forth fruits of unright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs, by which the Lord is provoked unto wrath and diſpleaſure; he that Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man for his own glory; but behold
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35378:9"/>man is become alive, and a Servant unto him that did not abide in the truth, and is become an alien and a ſtranger unto him who is the God of all truth, from whence every good and perfect gift proceeds, who ſent forth of his own life into the World a perfect gift to enlighten it, the word of life by which all things was made, and the life which had been ſlain from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world did he manifeſt again in the world, to reconcile thoſe again unto himſelf that did believe, that they might receive his knowledg again, which through tranſgreſſion they had loſt; that man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came without ſenſe or feeling of the love, life, glory and power which God at firſt placed him in; that he became bruitiſh in his knowledge, and drinketh in iniquity as the Oxe the water; that all fleſh hath corrupted its way; that none doth good, no not one. Hear is the eſtate of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the fall, ſeperated from God by that enmity which is unreconcilable; namely the carnal mind which is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Gods Law, neither indeed can be; So the appearance of God again unto man, and in man is by his own gift with which he hath enlightened him, in reproving of him for his tranſgreſſion, and in ſhewing him how he is a ſervant of ſin, and how
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35378:9"/>that death and the curſe hath paſſed over him, and how they have ſwallowed him up, and how Hell and the powers of darkneſs hath prevailed againſt him; and that which gives man to ſee this, is the gift of God, with which he is enlightened; and they that comes to be redeemed again unto God, will firſt ſee how theſe things hath ruled over them, and alſo they will ſee there is no other way whereby any can be redeemed from under the power of death and Hell, but by believing in the gift which comes from God; nor that they can attain unto life, ſtrength, and Salvation any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way but by receiving, and walking in the gift with which they are enlightened, the appearance of which is pure as I ſaid unto thee; who did enquire what the light led into, and what it led from; now thou that hath ſtopped thy ears at its cry, thou mayeſt ſee darkneſs hath prevailed, and death hath taken hold; that under the power of them thou yet fitteth; and this is the ſtate and condition of all that ſtops the eare at the cry of the light in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which cryes for purity and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs; that I may anſwer thee in ſhort, purity, and righteouſneſs, is that which the light, (unto which I inform thee) leads into, and impurity, and unrighteouſneſs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35378:10"/>is that it leads from; for impureneſs is contrary to its nature, and that is it which the light condemns for, as thou may well remember how often it hath reproved thee, and broken thy peace, when thou followed thy own hearts luſts, in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe things which thy heart luſted after; and alſo thou mayeſt remember that at ſome times when thou gave heed to it, and by it was reſtrained from the evil, that it raiſed up ſome good deſires in thy heart to walk in the way of God, and to come out of the vanitie which thy mind was captivated by; wch deſires I hope thou art not yet wholly without, though thou haſt followed ſuch guides and teachers long that hath laboured to perſwade thee, that the light of which I now ſpeak is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, to wit, the light which ſhews thee thy ſin and darkneſs, which if thou would hearken to, would let thee ſee that thy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſuch guides and teachers hath been a great cauſe of thy ſo long travel in this great darkneſs, which thou art ſenſible thou art yet in, and out of it none but the Lord alone can deliver thee; therefore his light he hath placed in thee freely, to ſhew thee the darkneſs in which thy mind is enſnared, and thy ſoul captivated, and his light is freely given unto thee, to lead
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35378:10"/>thee out of it, and doth not come by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man interpret and give his meanings upon the Scripture, but is freely given of God; which make thoſe which ſays light and faith comes by hearing them ſpeak their imaginations of the Scriptures, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach it, and call it natural; to wit the light (which convinces of ſin) which is the free gift of God, and cannot be bought and ſold for money, as thoſe that calls this light natural do their meanings which they give of the Scriptures, which were ſpoken forth freely from the gift of God, and are of no private interpretation, ne ther came by the will of man, but are to be read and fulfilled in the ſame ſpirit by which they were ſpoken forth; though ſuch as deny the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one withall, ſell their meanings and interpretations which they give of them, and calls ſo doing preaching of the word; and tells people light and faith muſt come by hearing of them; but the Lord is diſcovering of their whoredom and redeeming his flock out of their mouths, and the Scriptures alſo, that they ſhall deceive the ſimple no longer by their falſe interpreting of them, and by their falſe meanings which they have given of them, for the Lord is bringing his out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35378:11"/>Captivity, and freeing them into his own Covenant of light where they ſhall be taught of him, and ſhall not need to ſay every man to his neighbour and to his Brother, know the Lord; for they ſhall all know him from the greateſt to the leaſt. So thou that haſt adhered to ſuch teachers as told thee that the light which convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thee of ſin, and ſhewed thee thy own darkneſs, was not ſufficient to lead unto Salvation; but told thee of a greater light which muſt come by hearing them, which muſt free thee from the condemning power of ſin, though not from that power by which it is brought forth. I ſay unto thee, by ſuch thou haſt been kept in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, that thy ſin hath ſtill ruled and had power over thee; and thou ſtill by the light in thy Conſcience art condemned for it; that the King of peace thou waſt not like to know, nor his Salvation which thou ſaieſt thy Soul longed for; in that thou haſt rejected his light which appeared in thee to convert thy heart unto himſelf; but thou not believing in it, but adhering unto ſuch as told thee it was but natural, thou ſtill haſt remained a ſtranger unto him, though thou waſt diligent in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving thoſe things which the Kingdome of God comes not by, for it comes not by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35378:11"/>obſervation, neither ſtands in Words, but in Power, of which thou daily wilt partake as the light (which thou ſo long has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected) comes to be thy guide, in which thou wilt feel life, glory, and vertue ſpring forth; and then thou wilt clearly ſee they that told thee the light (which ſhewed thee thy own ſin) was naturall, are enemies unto thy Soules reſt and peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Captive, </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>According to my promiſe and thy deſirent, I have lent a diligent ear, and taken good notice of thy words; that I do plainly ſee, the cauſe of this my ſo much darkneſs and long travell, and running from Mountain to Hill, hath been becauſe I have not been informed to this light, of the appearance and of the operation of which thou haſt ſpoken; that gladly I would be further informed concerning it, how I may diſcern the appearance of it in my ſelf; ſeeing thou ſaith that I and all men have a meaſure of it given unto us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Inform,</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>Seeing thou art ſenſible that the cauſe of thy great darkneſs and wandring aſtray hath been becauſe thou hath not been informed to this light, of the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance &amp; operation of which I have ſpoken; therefore I ſhall endeavour to inform thee how thou maieſt know the appearance of it in thy ſelf, by its nature and quality;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35378:12"/>for its contrary to all uncleanneſs either of fleſh or ſpirit, and ſtands a witneſs in thee for the Lord, bearing Teſtimony in thy own Conſcience that he is againſt all unrighteouſneſs, impurity and unholineſs; that when thou goes into theſe things, he by his light reproves thee, and ſhews thee thou ought not to give thy ſtrength nor yeild thy members ſervants to ſuch things; but that thou ought to give thy ſtrength, and yield thy members Servants unto him, who by his light calls for purity, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Equity, and Juſtice in all things; and this is that which thy God requires of thee, to love mercy, and to do juſtly, and to walk humbly with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſay'ſt I may diſcern the appearance of this light, (to which thou doſt inform me) by its nature, and quality, in that its contrary to all unrighteouſneſſe, and reproves me when I go into it; which thing I do plainly ſee, and am very ſenſible of, that it doth condemn me and trouble me, when I act any unrighteouſneſs; but the thing I deſire to know, whether if I take heed unto it, it will keep me out of the unrighteouſneſs, which it is ſo ready to reprove and condemn me for.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Inform.</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>Thou being ſenſible (as thou ſaith thou art) that the light to which I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35378:12"/>inform thee, to wit, that in thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that it is very ready to reprove and trouble thee when thou acts any unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; well according to thy Querie I ſhall anſwer thee. The light to which I inform thee, is that which ſhews thee when thou haſt an evil intent or purpoſe in thy heart, to wrong any, or to do any injuſtice in what ſort ſoever; now if thou take heed unto that wch ſhews thee how theſe things would conceive in thy heart, then thou wilt learn true judgment within thy ſelf, whereby the evil and ſelf (that would joyn with it) will be judged; that when the evil before mentioned would appear to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, it by the true light wilbe condemned; and ſo thou having thy mind exerciſed in the Principle of light; thou wilt feel the ſufficencie and ability that is in it, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the evil in its appearance; and as thou comes to feel this, indeed and in truth, then thou wilt know the light which was ſo ready to condemn and trouble thee, when unrighteouſneſs was committed, as ready to give peace and preſerve thee out of all the ſnares and temptations of the wicked one, who hath long led thee Captive at his will, in that thy mind hath not been informed, directed nor guided by the true eternal light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35378:13"/>
Cap. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truly I ſee and am very ſenſible of this alſo, the cauſe why my ſin hath ſo prevailed over me, is becauſe I have not taken heed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this light which ſhewed me when temptations did ariſe in my own heart; but that I have given way unto them, that ſin hath been brought forth, and it hath brought forth death, under the ſhaddow of which (as I told thee at firſt) I yet ſit; but me thinks I am ſome-what encouraged for the time to come to take heed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this light thou informs me unto, in that thou ſaith, ſufficency and ability is in it to overcome the evil in its appearance; and in that alſo thou ſaith, as, by it am kept out of the evil, it will be as ready to give peace as ever it was to trouble and condemn me when I had committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; and as I remember thou told me it is able to keep and preſerve me out of all the ſnares and temptations of the wicked one, which thing hath not been counted credible by either Teachers or people, among whom I have walked; but we have rather cryed out as hereſy, and blaſphemy that any ſhould ſay they are free from ſin in this life; but indeed ſince I fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conference with thee, and that thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed me to this light within, and that by it I feel my underſtanding ſomewhat opened; I dare not judge it as a thing unpoſſible, but that people may be throughly waſhed and cleanſed by the blood of Jeſus from all ſin and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35378:13"/>while hear upon Earth; that if it ſhould pleaſe the Lord to open thy mouth to inform me any further, I ſhould gladly lend an eare.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Inform.</hi> 
               </speaker>
               <p>Well, being thou ſeeſt the cauſe why thy ſin hath ſo prevailed againſt thee, hath been becauſe thou haſt not taken heed to the light, which ſhewed thee when temptations did ariſe in thy own heart; and ſeeing thou haſt received ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement for the time to come to take heed unto it, namely the light which I did inform thee unto, which hath ſhewed thee thy own darkneſs; now that thou may mind thy own condition, I perceive that is ſafe for thee and not to ſeek to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend things in thy own wiſdome; but wait to feel thy ſelf comprehended into the light which thou told me at our firſt entring into conference, thou hadſt a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be freed into; for conſider dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is that which thou haſt been captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by, and light is that which hath been hidden from thine eyes; but now thou finding it ſomewhat opening thy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is ſafe for thee to abide in it, and not to reach at things above thy meaſure, leaſt thou be beguiled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived again; for as I told thee before, thy ſtrength, ſufficiency, and ability
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35378:14"/>in the meaſure of light, which thou ſaith in ſome meaſure hath opened thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; that if thou go before it, thou goes from thy ſtrength and ſtay; and then the enemie which thou haſt been ſo long captivated by, he can toſs thy mind, and lead thee what way it pleaſeth him; ſo in ſhort thy profiting unto God ſtands in thy own meaſure of light received from Chriſt; for abiding in it, thou wilt ſee more light, and witneſs the Day-ſtar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in thy heart, which will be more joy, gladneſs, comfort, and ſatisfaction unto thy ſoul, then ever thou taſted of, while thou followed ſuch Teachers, and walked amongſt ſuch people that cryed hereſie, and blaſphemy, that any ſhould expect to be freed from ſin in this life. For thou mayeſt remember while thou walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch, that thou was wholly in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for thy ear was ſtopped at the cry of the light, which now in ſome meaſure hath opened thy underſtanding, that thou dare not judge that is impoſſible, but that they which believe may be Cleanſed throughly by the blood of Jeſus. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is none but ſuch teachers and people that calls the light natural (ſuch thou told me thou did adhere unto in the time when thou was ſo toſſed from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35378:14"/>Mountain to Hill) that cryes hereſie and blaſphemy, that any ſhould ſay they are freed from ſin in this life; but now thy underſtanding being ſomewhat opened by the true light, thou ſees all things poſſible with God; but while thou ſtood wholy in that nature which hated the light, thou was in the unbelief, and ſo judged accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy blindneſs; and as thou ſaw it was in thy ſelf, and meaſured the Saints conditions by thy own; as <hi>Paul</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that thou knows full well thoſe teachers, and people that hates the light, which Chriſt hath enlightned every one withal, and calls it natural, that they cannot believe any ſuch thing, that any ſhould be wholly cleanſed from ſin while here upon Earth, but accounts it as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion that any ſhould have ſuch a faith in them that they may be wholy clenſed; but little I hope, I need to ſay unto thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them; for thou knows well thy ſelf upon what a bad Foundation thy faith ſtood while thou followed ſuch Teachers, and walked among ſuch people, <hi>Videlicet</hi> ſuch as cryed
Hereſie and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that any ſhould ſay they witneſs free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from ſin while here upon Earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35378:15"/>
Captive. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hope the Lord will further ſhew me the things which long I have ſought after; for this now I plainly ſee that my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting unto God, ſtands onely in the meaſure of Light, which Chriſt hath enlightened me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; and alſo the Lord through his tender mercyes with the day from on high by which he hath viſited me, hath letten me ſee that the cauſe of all this my want hath been, that I have not minded my own Condition, but hath rather ſought to comprehend things in my Earthly wiſdom, which now I ſee is fooliſhneſs with God, and hath ſeparated me from the knowledge of his wayes, that I was not like to ſee into thoſe things which do pertain unto life eternal, neither into the Saints Conditions which I read on in the Scriptures; becauſe I knew not a meaſure of this Light within to be my guide, which now I ſee the Scriptures were ſpoken forth from, and remains as dark ſayings unto me and all men, untill our underſtandings comes to be opened by the true light which leads to the fulfilling of them. For as thou ſayeſt while my ear was ſtopped againſt the cry of the true light, then I meaſured the Saints Conditions, and judged of them according to my own darkneſs; for the faith I was in (or rather unbelief) gave me no victory over my ſin, in that I did not believe in the Light which Chriſt had enlightned me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; though I profeſſed faith in him, and did
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35378:15"/>ſtrive many times within my ſelf to believe that all my ſins paſt and to come were done away in him; yet ſtill this light which came from him (namely Chriſt) and ſhined into my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, did ſhew me that my ſins were ſtanding and was unblotted out; and that I was an enemy in my mind unto his life, in that ſin was brought forth, and that with my mind I ſerved it; and as thou ſaid my faith ſtood upon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Foundation, as</hi> I <hi>now plainly ſee; for it was gathered from without me and not from any knowledge of Chriſt made manifeſt within me, the hope of my glory, but was wholly built upon my own Imaginations, which did ariſe out of that ground which did hate the appearance of Gods grace; that when it at any time did appear, reproving me for the vanity my mind was run into, it was rejected, in that the teachers (whom I followed) told me it was but a reſtraining grace and not ſaving; and by their perſwading of me I was ſtrengthned in my Imaginations; that I went on in rebellion, not taking heed to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Gods grace, which did appear to lead me out of my ſin and vain converſation; but being perſwaded by the aforeſaid Teachers that I muſt not expect ſuch a thing as to be freed from ſin in this life, this pleaſed my carnal mind and ſtrengthned me to go on in Rebellion againſt the light which did condemn me for it; that I would have reaſoned; had not</hi> Paul <hi>a body
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35378:16"/>of Sin? and what muſt I expect to be freed from ſin more then he? But indeed in all that time</hi> I <hi>thus reaſoned, I never had true peace, neither indeed was like to have; for now I ſee that it was the enemy of my Souls reſt and peace that thus reaſoned and pleaded for ſin, which is the Devils Kingdome; and that they are his Miniſters that perſwades people that they muſt not expect to be freed from ſin ſo long as they live, which new</hi> I <hi>ſee is a Sold-deſtroying Doctrine, and is not received by any, but they that be in the unbelief; for as</hi>I <hi>told thee ſince my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding was ſomewhat opened by the true light,</hi> I <hi>ſee all things poſſible with God, and that faith as a grain of Muſtard-feed, is able to remove Mountains; that though</hi> I <hi>ſee the body of ſin yet ſtanding,</hi> I <hi>dare not but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he who by his appearance hath given me to ſee it, is able to deſtroy it and as thou knows well this is my condition at preſent, that gladly</hi> I <hi>would be further informed; for</hi> I <hi>find</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaks of ſuch a condition, and ſpeaks of an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming alſo; that</hi> I <hi>would know whether he witn ſſed an overcoming any other way but through the light, which gave him to ſee that ſin was grown up to have a body.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Inform.</speaker>
               <p>Being thou art ſenſible that this ſeaſoning with fleſh and blood, and following ſuch Teachers as did pleaſe the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35378:16"/>Carnal mind, in pleading for ſin, hath been it that hath cauſed thee to err from the way of thy Souls reſt and peace; which was wholly hidden from thine eyes while thou regarded not, but ſtopped thy ear at the cry of the Light, which Chriſt hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened thee withall; and while thou framed a faith according to thy own Imaginations, which gave thee no victory over Sin; but that with thy mind thou ſerved it, in fulfilling thy own hearts luſts, which led thee a ſide, and warred againſt thy Soul, which now thou art to wait to be delivered from; to know Chriſt thy Souls Saviour to be revealed in his own light the hope of thy glory; to deſtroy and take away thy ſin which long hath ſeperated &amp; alienated thy mind from the life of God; that thou haſt been a ſtranger unto his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Promiſe, by reaſon of the hardneſs and impudency, that thy heart was hardened in, by conſulting
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35378:17"/>with thy imaginations, and by lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an ear to ſuch as perſwaded thee, that the appearance of the grace of God (which did appear to lead thee out of thy ſin and vaine converſation, was but a reſtraining grace, and not able to ſave thy Soul. Oh blindneſs and ignorance, that ever thou or any ſhould lend an ear to ſuch; Is not the grace which is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain from ſin, ſaving? For what would thou or any be ſaved from, if not from ſin? For hath not ſin been it that hath kept your Souls in death; and is not ſin the cauſe of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation? And is not the grace ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving which the Apoſtle ſaith hath appeared unto all men; which taught them that denying ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, they ſhould live godly and ſoberly in this preſent world; that ſo as long as thou rejected the appearance of this grace thou was not like to know Redemption from thy Sin, and vain converſation; For
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35378:17"/>thou confeſt thy carnal mind which is at enmity with God, was at liberty and ſtrengthened, which the grace appeared to mortifie; but it having been pleaſed, thou wert not like to pleaſe God, nor to obtain mercy with him to overcome thy ſin, but was ſhort of the life the Saints was in that ſpoke forth the Scripture, and ſo could not meaſure their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor ſee into the myſtery the Scripture ſpeaks of; thou being in the unbelief, and reprobated in thy mind in that, with it thou ſerved ſin, in fulfilling the luſts of it; that ſo thou may ſee there hath been a great difference betwen the condition that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of (about which thou reaſoned) and thine; For he in that time when he ſaw the Law of ſin, which was in his members, warring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of his mind, and the wretched ſtate; he with his mind ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Lord, but thou ſin, as thou coufeſſeth in that time, when thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35378:18"/>egarded not, but diſ-eſteemed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the light which appeared, ſhewing thee thy ſin; but now the Day-ſpring from on High, having vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited thee, thou plainly ſees that faith as a grain of muſtard ſeed is able to remove Mountains; that I may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee in ſhort, the overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks on, and witneſſed, was obtained through the Law of the Spirit of Life, which firſt: diſcovered the body of ſin unto him, and the wretched eſtate which made him cry out who ſhould deliver him? how the Law of the ſpirit of life which was in Chriſt, that delivered him, and ſet him free from the Law of ſin, and Death; which for a time was in his Members.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Captive. </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What thou haſt ſpoken I clearly ſee is Truth; for I finde the light in my own Conſcience bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to it; which Light alſo I now ſee is to be my guide; and for the want of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35378:18"/>the knowledge of it, I long have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, and erred in judgement, in the things pertaining to my ſouls peace; and eſpecially about the appearance of the Light, which long I deſired to ſee; and though it was near me, even in my own Conſcience; yet being drawn aſide, by an evil heart of unbeliefe, and by ſuch teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as was in the ſame unbeliefe; I have ſtumbled at the true light, which appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo near me, which the Lord through his viſitation hath cauſed to ſhine forth of darkneſs; that all the dark wayes, in which I have long walked, and gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray in, I now clearly ſee and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; that I hope for the time to come, the Lord will giude my feet in the way of peace, in that he hath ſhewed, and made manifeſt unto me, a meaſure of his own light, to prepare me a way through the wilderneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that though I walk through the valley of the ſhaddow of death, yet I will not fear, ſeeing the Lords love hath ſo largely extended to me; that after the time of this long darkneſs, he hath cauſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35378:19"/>Light to ſhine forth, and his day to ſpring from on High which hath light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon me, that hath long ſitten in darkneſs, and long gone aſtray as a ſheep having no ſhepherd; and that hath been as in a pit, where there hath been no water, and hath lain long as in a Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of wofull darkneſs, under the chains of which I have long been kept, even nigh without hopes of deliverance; yet now I ſee the Lord hath fulfilled his Promiſes, who ſaid he would give him that ſhould he for a Covenant of light un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that ſat in darkneſs; and to bring forth the Priſoners out of the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; and to deliver the Captive out of Captivity, and to Proclaim liberty, &amp; the acceptable yeare, &amp; the day of vengeance; to comfort thoſe that mourned. And the Lord hath according to his Promiſe, ſought out that which was loſt and is bringing back that which hath been driven away, and hath been ſcattered in the Cloudy, and dark day; in which I (with many more) were deceived by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35378:19"/>ſuch Teachers as before I told thee of; who called the Light which Chriſt hath enlightened every one with all, naturals and ſuch as ſet up their own imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and carnal Ordinances; and tells peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they muſt obſerve them, and wait for the appearance of Chriſt in; and ſuch as tells people they muſt live in ſin, as long as they live; let me be a warning to all, for following ſuch Teachers any longer; who long was led a ſtray by ſuch, from the light which now (through the viſitation of God), I ſee is my way, guide, and leader into the fold of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt; the appearance of which I found very near me, though I ſtumbled at it until I was Informed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:35378:20"/>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35378:20"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>MUch more might be written (then here is) concerning the viſiting and bringing of the Captive forth of captivity; but this is the ſum of all, the eternal and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light having ſhined forth; which as it is waited in, diſcovereth, and breaketh the chains of darkneſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the captive hath been kept in the grievous oppreſſion by the ſin and corruption, which hath abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and been brought forth through the motions of the evil; which the light being received and believed in, will ſhew the appearance of; and ſo as its walked in, take away the evil, and the bond of corruption; and will reveal life, and bring deliverance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35378:21"/>unto the captive, by taking away the evil in its apearance, whereby the mind with the true light, will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and guided up unto God, who hath immortallitie and dwelleth in that light which no mortal eye can approach unto; but is onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed as the mind is made ſingle by the taking away of the darkneſs, which makes the eye of every ones mind evil (that doth not believe in the light which Chriſt hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned every one withall), that their whole body is filled full of darkneſs, and yet the light ſhineth in darkneſs, by which the captive (which through the darkneſs is kept in captivity)is viſited through the tender mercyes of the Lord, who ſo loved the world that he gave his onely begotten Son a light into it, which enlightneth every one that cometh into the world that through the light they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be ſaved from the darkneſs which hath blinded the eye of all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35378:21"/>man-kind, untill they came to feel the true light in themſelues diſcovering the darkneſs unto them, and leading them from it. And ſo as this is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, the eye is made good again; and ſo comes the body to be filled full of light, in which the ſeed (which hath been captivated through the darkneſs) rejoyceth, and praiſeth the Lord for his deliverance; that I ſay this is the ſume of all (the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the true Light being felt) though much more might be written concerning the releaſe and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Captive, and Priſoner of hope; for darkneſs is onely that which doth Captivate and Impriſon; that light is onely that which muſt lead out of it; and concerning this light, of the appearance and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of which I have ſpoken, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all ſuch as feels themſelves captivated with the darkneſs but many of the Servants of the Lord (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me) hath written large and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35378:22"/>Declarations, for the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch as have any true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in them, to be freed from that great &amp; groſs darkneſs which lieth over all, in the fall &amp; tranſgreſſion, &amp; alſo that ſuch as deſpiſeth the viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God might be left without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; that the things which we bear Teſtimony of, is not of our ſelves, neither have we received them from man, but from God alone, whoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation and love we bear witneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, though by the world we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed for it; and unto ſuch I do not direct this, but unto them who are weary and feels the load of ſin, that they through the everlaſting light may be led from it to partake of the Power of the endleſs life, which freeth from the Power of death, which all are over-ſhaddowed by, till the day of viſitation ariſe upon them, which onely is known as the light is received which diſcovereth to every one their own darkneſs; that moſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35378:22"/>unhappy are they that doth reject the appearance of it; for ſuch letteth the day of their viſitation paſs over their heads that it will be hid from their eyes when they deſire to ſee it. So happy are they that while it is called to day, doth not harden their hearts againſt the reprofes of the light (which ſheweth unto them their own ſin and darkneſs but believes in it; for to that end it is given, that through it all might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and this is the true faith, and here the increaſe of it will be known, as the Light is obeyed, which from all Sin leadeth, unto Life eternal, all them doth follow it; and freeth the Soul from all captivity, and bondage, into peace and ſatisfaction, which they cannot receive who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecteth and turneth their Backs on the reproofes of the Light; unto which I have informed ſuch as have long layne in captivity, expecting freedom and help by obſerving of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35378:23"/>thoſe things which life comes not by; for he that is the Light (unto which I inform) is the life alſo, that what is wanting, is in the Light to be waited for.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
